Guide to the E. S. Reddy Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional material, 1963-1995; Accession 1996-M-002
  - Subject files of printed material
    - Mayibuye Centre for History and Culture in South Africa, Circa 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Namedia Foundation (Media Foundation of the Non-aligned Research and Publications Centre), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Newspapers, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Non-Governmental Organizations (NGO) Committee on Southern Africa, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Office of the South African Consul General, NY ["Women and Change in South Africa," conference ], 1995 April (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Oil Embargo Against South Africa [newsletter], 1993 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Organization of African Unity
      Includes information about the Permanent Observer Mission of the Organization of African Unity to the United Nations.
      - Chronology, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Reports, resolutions, 1965-1984 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Press releases, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Pan Africanist Congress of Azania (PAC), 1993 August (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - South African History Archive, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Southern Africa Education Program, Stony Point, NY, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Umxoxi [publication of the KwaZulu Government], 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - United Nations
      - Africa Group, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Children's Fund (UNICEF), 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Department of Public Information, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Development Fund for Women (UNIFEM), 1995 July (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Development Programme, 1995 October (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO), 1995 July (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Industrial Development Organization, 1995 July (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Information Center for India and Bhutan, 1984 August (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Permanent Mission of Germany to the United Nations, 1995 October (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Permanent Mission of Japan to the United Nations, 1996 March (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Permanent Mission of South Africa to the United Nations
        - Background papers, 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 43)
        - Miscellaneous papers, 1992, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 44)
        - News highlights, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 45-47)
        - Press releases, 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 48-49)
      - Permanent Mission of the Republic of Angola to the United Nations, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Permanent Observer Office of the International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies at the United Nations, 1996 March (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - Special Committee Against Apartheid, 1976 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - United Kingdom Mission, 1995 August (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - United States Conference of Mayors, 1995 January (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - University of the Western Cape [includes Historical and Cultural Center], 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - The World Bank, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - World Health Organization, 1996 February (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Speeches
    - Gambari, Ibrahim A. [Chairman of the UN Special Committee Against Apartheid; Ambassador/Permanent Representative of Nigeria to the UN], 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 58-62)
    - Gandhi, Indira [Prime Minster of India; message to the International Conference on Women and Apartheid, organized by the United Nations, Brussels], 1982 April 30 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Garba, Joseph [Permanent Representative of Nigeria to the United Nations; "Nigeria in the United Nations: The Pursuit of National Interest in a Global Forum"], 1988 November (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Mdlalose, F. T. [KwaZulu-Natal Premier], 1994, May- September (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Writings
    - Laher, M. S. [on the evils of alcohol and modern dance], undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Reddy, E. S., "India and South Africa: A Collection of Papers" [Occasional Papers Series: No. 1], 1991 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Wright, Abdur-Rahmaan, "The Black People of South Africa and the Imported Religions" [2nd ed.], undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
- Additional material, 1963-1996; Accession 1996-M-129
  - Subject files [primarily printed material]
    - The Africa Fund, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - African National Congress (ANC)
      - Fundraising appeals, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Mayibuye [journal of ANC], 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Reconstruction and Development Programmme (RDP), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - South Africa Freedom News, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Anti-Apartheids Beweging Nederland, "The Cultural Voice of the Resistance: Dutch and South African Artists Against Apartheid" [workshop, Amsterdam], 1982 December (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Artistes du Monde contre l'Apartheid, "Art contre/against Apartheid" [exhibit in cooperation with the United Nations Special Committee against Apartheid, 1983 Nov], 1981-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Border Rural Committee, GroundWork, 1966 December (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Fondation Culturelle Contre l'Apartheid, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Human Rights Trust, Monitor, 1989 July (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - International Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Irish Anti-Apartheid Movement, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Legal Resources Center, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Academie Nationale de Médicine, 1982 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Non-Governmental Organizations (NGO) Committee on Southern Africa, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Organization of African Unity
      - The African Group [group of states at the United Nations], 1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Meetings in Accra, Ghana, 1965 October (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Relationship with the United Nations [correspondence, memoranda], 1965-1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Phelps Stokes Fund, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Schomburg Center, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - South African Consulate General, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - United Nations
      - Center against Apartheid [material pertaining to a cultural boycott of South Africa], 1979-1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Division for the Advancement of Women, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Permanent Mission of South Africa, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Permanent Mission of the Federal Republic of Germany, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Permanent Mission of the Republic of Sierra Leone, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Permanent Observer Mission of the Organization of African Unity, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - University of Fort Hare, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - University of Pittsburgh, PA, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Speeches
    - Laclaustra, Arturo [Deputy Permanent Representative of Spain on behalf of the European Union: statement given at the fiftieth session of the General Assembly], 1995 December (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Maitama-Sule, Alhaji Yusuff [Minister of National Guidance of Nigeria; given at the University of Picardie], 1983 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Additional material, 1960-1996; Accession 1997-M-093
  - "Oliver Tambo: Speeches, Interviews, and Papers, 1960-1993" [draft compiled by E. S. Reddy]
    - 1960-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
      Includes table of contents, list of abbreviations, and glossary.
    - 1986-1993 (Box 2, Folder 8-11)
- Additional material, 1963-2001; Accession 1997-M-116
  - Subject files [printed material]
    - Africa Action, 2001 (Box 1)
    - The Africa Fund, 1996-2001 (Box 1)
    - African National Congress (ANC), 1991-1997, undated (Box 1)
    - Alliance of Africans in the Americas, 1997 (Box 1)
    - American Committee on Africa (ACOA), 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - Anti-Apartheid Movement (London), 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Black Heritage Festival ["Rediscover Your Roots"], 2001 May (Box 1)
    - British Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Freedom Day Celebrations [Embassy of South Africa], 2000 April-June (Box 1)
    - International Committee of the Red Cross, 1998, 2000 June (Box 1)
    - Kwa Muhle Museum (Durban), 1991 (Box 1)
    - Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Organization of African Unity (OAU), 1994, 1997-1998, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
    - Pan Africanist Congress (PAC), 1993 (Box 1)
    - Permanent Mission of South Africa to the United Nations, 1993, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
    - Robben Island Exhibition and Information Centre (Cape Town), [1996?] (Box 1)
    - South African Consulate-General [correspondence], 1994 (Box 1)
    - South African High Commission, Insight, 1999 Winter (Box 1)
    - This Week in South Africa, 1995-1997 (Box 1)
    - United Nations Department of Public Information, 1963-2000 (Box 1)
    - University of Namibia, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
- Additional material, 1956-1981; Accession 2003-M-072
  - "Chronological Review of Developments Concerning Sports and Apartheid", 1956-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notes on meeting with Josef M. Luns [secretary-general of NATO], 1975 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- Additional material, 1961-1985; Accession 2003-M-092
  - Microfilm of typescript letterbooks of E. S. Reddy
    Letterbooks pertain to the work of the U.N. Centre Against Apartheid and the U.N. Special Committee Against Apartheid; originals were returned to donor
    Duplicating masters of microfilm may not be used. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository.
    - Duplicating master, 1961-1981 (Reel 1-D)
      - Use copy (Reel 1U)
    - Duplicating master, 1982-1984 April (Reel 2-D)
      - Use copy (Reel 2U)
    - Duplicating master, 1984 April-1985 December (Reel 3-D)
      - Use copy (Reel 3U)
- Additional material, 1990-1991; Accession 2003-M-093
  - Microfilm of "Islam in South Africa: Miscellaneous Documents," duplicating master, 1990-1991 (Reel 1-D)
    Original returned to donor.
    - Use copy (Reel 1U)
- Additional material, 1963-2005; Accession 2005-M-098
  The accession is comprised of correspondence, conference materials, and pamphlets. The materials are organized alphabetically by personal name, organization, or title.
  - Africa Action, letters, solicitations, invitation to organization's 50th anniversary celebration, 2001-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - African National Congress, 1974-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - African Union to the U.N., Circa 2004 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The American Fund for Free Jurists, 1969 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anti-apartheid conferences, United States, 1972-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Chief Lutuli and the United Nations", 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Document assembled by E. S. Reddy from copies of correspondence from various individuals
  - "Commemorating the Centenary of Phoenix Settlement, 1904-2004", Circa 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Committee to Stop the Davis Cup, 1977 March-April (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dee, Rudy, "My One Good Nerve, A Visit with Rudy Dee" [invitation to the opening night gala at the Schomberg Center for Research in Black Culture], 2000 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 50th Anniversary Council (of the 1946 Passive Resistance Campaign), 1996 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gandhi Committee, "Gandhi in South Africa", undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Institute of Political Science, University of Göteborg, 1972 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "The Liberation History Bulletin," vol. 1, nos. 8, 10, 13, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Liberation History Foundation, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Mobilisation Anti-Apartheid" [consortium of French anti-apartheid movements], 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Organization of African Unity (OAU), press releases, Communique of the 81st Ordinary Session of the Central Organ of the OAU Mechanism for Conflict Prevention, Management, and Resolution at Ambassadorial Level, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Reddy, E. S.
    - Correspondence, 1989 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Informal notes from a conference convened by the government of Sweden, "Apartheid, South Africa, and International Law, Selected Documents and Papers", 1985 December (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "United Nations and the International Campaign against Apartheid," conference paper, 2004 October (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - State of South Africa vs. Tahudaleni and Others G. Mbindi, 1969 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Study Project on External Investment in South Africa and Namibia, 1973 August 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Towards Ten Years of Freedom, Progress in the First Decade, Challenges in the Second Decade" [pamphlet], 2004 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - UNESCO, newsletter, press releases, 2002 March-August (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The Washington Office on Africa, 1984 February (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Additional material, 1964-2008; Accession 2007-M-016
  Also includes Accession 2009-M-098
  - General information about South Africa, Circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - African National Congress press release about Soweto, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Building Bridges: Publication of South Africa Partners, Inc., A People-to-People Development Organization, vol. 7, no. 2, 2005 Fall (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Canon Collins Educational Trust for Southern Africa, fundraising literature, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Don't Mourn, Mobilise: A Tribute to M. P. Naicker, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - International Seminar on the UN Arms Embargo Against South Africa, 1986 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Invitations and programs for events celebrating South Africa, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Permanent Mission of South Africa to the United Nations
    - Backgrounder No. 03/93, "Multi-party Negotiating Process Reaches Agreement on an Interim Constitution for the Transitional Period", 1993 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Chronology of Developments in South Africa, 1991 September-1994 January (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - News Highlights from the South African Media, 1993 October-1994 January (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Press Release, 1993 October 15, 1994 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - UN Resolution 435 and the Independence of Namibia, 1978 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - United Nations Special Committee Against Apartheid correspondence regarding committee enlargement, 1965-2008 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    The bulk of this correspondence dates from 1965-1966. Includes a 2008 reminiscence about the Committee by E. S. Reddy.
  - Correspondence from Oliver Tambo to E. S. Reddy, excerpts and explanatory material supplied by Reddy, 1964-1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Excerpted correspondence dates from 1964-1973
- Additional material, 1961-2007; Accession 2010-M-051; 0.5
  Arrangement
  Arranged as received from the African Collection curator.
  This accession comprises writings by E.S. Reddy and others, printed ephemera and correspondence relating to contemporary issues in Africa, and a tile by a South African artist.
  - Krishna Menon: Selected Speeches at the United Nations / E. S. Reddy and A. K. Damodaran, typescript, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Reminiscences of E. S. Reddy on the United Nations, Nelson Mandela, Chief Lituli, and Kaiser Matanzima, Circa 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bibliography of publications by E. S. Reddy, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diallo-Telli Foundation, prospectus, Circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Davids, Karima, tile painiting of the Aljamia Mosque in Cape Town, South Africa, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and printed ephemera relating to contemporary issues in Africa, Circa 1970-circa 2005 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Inventory of the Oliver Tambo Collection at the University of Witwatersrand, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Writings by E. S. Reddy on the United Nations Special Committee Against Apartheid, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "History of the International Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa (IDAF)," unpublished draft, 1961-2007 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Prepared by Diana Collins and Phyllis Altman in 1961; accompanied by a 2007 explanatory note from E. S. Reddy.
- Additional material, 1971-2010; Accession 2014-M-017; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Greeting cards, Circa 1989-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subject files
    - Anti-apartheid, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - World Peace Council, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Italy and aircraft industry in South Africa, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) and South Africa, 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - International Exchange Fund, 1976, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Writings
    - "Gandhi and Africans in South Africa", 1993 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "International University Exchange Fund, Its Rise and Demise: My Reminiscences", 2010 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Italy and the Aircraft Industry in South Africa: My Reminiscences", 2010 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "NATO and South Africa: My Reminiscences", 2010 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "The World Peace Council, the United Nations and the ANC: My Reminiscences", 2010 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Additional material, 1956-1999; Accession 2015-M-002
  - Photocopies of documents concerning Chief Lutuli, 1953-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of International Consultation on Archives and Archival Material of the International Campaign Against Apartheid, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)